<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable and necessary warning and declaration concerning present and imminent dangers, and concerning duties relating thereto from the Generall Assembly of this Kirk : vnto all the members thereof.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58911</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13691444</idno>
  <idno type="VID">101400</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248502416</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34061</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13691444</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58911)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1047:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable and necessary warning and declaration concerning present and imminent dangers, and concerning duties relating thereto from the Generall Assembly of this Kirk : vnto all the members thereof.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edynburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of Scotland --  History.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101400:1"/>
            <p>A SEASONABLE AND NECESSARY WARNING AND DECLARATION, CONCERNING Present and Imminent Dangers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Duties relating thereto from the GENERALL ASSEMBLY OF THIS KIRK Vnto all the Members thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDYNBƲRGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings Most Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majesty, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101400:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101400:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>27. <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1649.</date>
                  <hi>Sess.</hi> 27.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>A seasonable and necessary Warning and Declaration, concerning Present and Imminent dangers, and concerning du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties relating thereto, from the General Assembly of this Kirk, unto all the Members thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord who chooses Jerusalem in a furnace of Affliction, hath been pleased since the beginning of the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in this Land, to exercise his People with many trialls; all that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to keep a good conscience, were not long agoe under many heavy and sad pressures from the insolency and oppression of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing party of dis-affected and Malignant men, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretext of bringing the King to a condition of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Freedom and Safety, did carry on an unlawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101400:3"/>against the Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> and if the Lord had not been mercifull unto his people, they were like either to have been banished out of the Land, or to have been kept in a perpetuall bondage in their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, persons and estates: But he whose Messengers those men had mocked, and whose word they had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised, did bring them down suddenly in a day, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored liberty and peace unto his people, a mercy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, which as it ought to be remembred with thankfulnesse and praise, so may it engage our hearts not to faint in troubles and straites that do yet abide us, but to trust in the name of the Lord, who both can and will deliver us still out of all our afflictions.</p>
            <p>Albeit, wee do now enjoy many rich and precious blessings wherein we have reason to be comforted, and to rejoyce; yet it were to shut our own eyes if we should not see our selves involved in, and threatned with many and great dangers at home and from abroad. It is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of exceeding great sorrow to think upon the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and profanity, the impenitencie and security that abounds still in the Land, notwithstanding all the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dispensation of the Gospel, and means of grace in such purity and plenty, that none of the Nations round about us 'can boast of the like, and of all the long-suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring patience of the Lord, and of all his sharp rods wherewith he hath afflicted us from year to year, and of all the mercies and deliverances wherewith he hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited us, and of our late solemn confession of sinnes, and engagement unto duties, sealed with the renewing of the Covenant and the Oath of God; Which some men have so far already forgotten, as to return with the dogge to the vomit, and with the sow to the puddle; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny signes of inconstancy and levity do appear among all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101400:3"/>sorts and ranks of persons, who seem to want nothing but a sutable tentation to draw them away from their steadfastnesse: Our Army is not yet sufficiently purged, but there be still in it Malignant and scandalous men, whose fidelity and constancy, as it is much to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, so is the wrath of the Lord to be feared, upon their proceedings and undertakings, without a speedy and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall remedy.</p>
            <p>That prevailing party of Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> who have broken the Covenant, and dispised the Oath of God, corrupted the truth, subverted the fundamentall Government by King and Parliament, and taken away the Kings life, look upon us with an evill eye, as upon these who stand in the way of their monstruous and new fangled devices in Religion and Government, and though there were no cause to fear any thing from that party but the Gangrene and infection of those many damnable and abominable errours which have taken hold on them, yet our vicinity unto, and daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with that Nation, may justly make us afraid that the Lord may give up many in this Land unto a spirit of delusion to beleeve lies, because they have not received the love of the truth.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Malignant party so far broken and brought low, as that they have abandoned all hopes of carrying on their former designs against the Covenant and work of Reformation, beside many of them in this Kingdom who are as Foxes tied in chains, keeping their evill nature, and waiting an oppertunity to break their cords, and again to prey upon the Lords people. There be standing Armies in Ireland, under the command of the Marquesse of Ormond, The Lord Inchqueen, the Lord of Airds and George Munro, who forgetting all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101400:4"/>the horrible cruelty that was exercised by the Irish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, upon many thousands of the English and Scottish Nations in that land, have entred into a Peace and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociation with them, that they may the more easily carry on the old designes of the Popish, Prelaticall and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party, and the Lord of <hi>Airds,</hi> and <hi>George Monroe,</hi> have by treachery and oppression brought the Province of <hi>Ulster,</hi> and Garrisons therein, under their Power and Command, and have redacted our country-men, and such as adhere unto the Covenant, and cause of God in that Province, unto many Miseries and Straits, and are like to banish the Ministers of the Gospell, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn these faire beginnings of the work of God, which were unto many a branch of hope, that the Lord meant to make <hi>Ireland</hi> a pleasant land.</p>
            <p>But which is more grievous unto us then all these, our King, Notwithstanding of the Lords hand against his Fathers opposition to the work of God, and of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sad and dolefull consequences that followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, in reference to Religion, and his Subjects and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and Government, doth barken unto the counsels of these, who were Authours of these miseries unto his Royall Father, and to his Kingdomes, by which it hath come to passe, that his Majesty hath hitherto refused to grant the just and necessary desires of this Kirk and Kingdom, which were tendred unto him from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners of both for securing of Religion, the Liberties of the Subject, his Majesties Government, and the Peace of the Kingdome; And it is much to be feared that those wicked Counsellours may so farre prevaile upon him in his tender yeers, as to engage him in a warre, for over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning (if it be possible) of the work of God, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down all those in the three Kingdomes that adhere
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101400:4"/>thereto, which if he shall doe, cannot but bring great wrath from the Lord upon himselfe and his Throne, and must be the cause of many new, and great miseries, and calamities to these Lands.</p>
            <p>It concerns a Nation thus sinfull and loaden with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and involved in so many difficulties and dangers, by timous repentance and unfained humiliation to draw near to God, and to wrestle with him in Prayer and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that our sin may be pardoned, and our iniquity done away, and that he would establish the Land in the love of the Truth, and inable every one in their station to doe their duty boldly and without fear, and in a hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dependance upon the Lord, in whom alone is the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his people; every man ought with all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and diligence, to make use of all these meanes that that are approven and allowed of God, for preserving and carrying on of his work, and for securing and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Land against all enemies whatsomever, both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the right hand and upon the lest.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of errour and delusion in our Neighbour-Land, in the policie of Satan hath vailed it selfe in many, under the mask of holinesse, and is in the righteous and wise dispensation of God, armed with power, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with successe. Therefore all the Inhabitants of this Land would labour for more knowledge, and more love of the truth, without which they may easily be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and led into tentation, and would learn to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish betwixt the shew and power of godlinesse; Wee know that there be many in <hi>England</hi> who be truly god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and mourn with us for all the errours and abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are in that land, but it is without controversie, that that Spirit which hath acted in the Courses and Counsels of these who hath retarded and obstructed the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101400:5"/>work of God, despised the Covenant, forced the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, murthered the King, changed the civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and estalished so vast a Toleration in Religion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Spirit of Righteousnesse and Holinesse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it teaches not men to live godly and righteously, but drawes them aside into errour, and makes them to bring forth the bitter fruits of impiety and iniquity, and therefore ought to be avoided; and not only are such of our Nation as travaile in our Neighbour-land, to take heed unto themselves, that they receive not infection from such as are leavened with Errour, but these also who live at home, especially in those places where Sectaries, upon pretext of merchandise, and other civill imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, ordinarily trasfique and converse: Neither needs any man to be afraid of the power and successe of that party, they who have gadded about so much to change their way, shall ere long be ashamed; the Lord hath reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted their confidences, and they shall not prosper in them. How farre they may proceed in their Resolutions and Actings against this Kingdome, is in the hand of the most high, if the Lord shall suffer that party to invade this land, it may be the comfort and incouragement of all the Inhabitants thereof, that not only hath that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull engagement against the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> been delared against, and condemned both by Kirk and State, but also that these men can pretend no quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell against us, unlesse it be that we have adhered unto the Solemn League and Covenant, from which they have so foully revolted &amp; backslidden, and that we have borne testimony against Toleration, and their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in reference to Religion and Government, and the taking away of the Kings life; and therefore we trust that in such a case none will be so farre deficient in their duty
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101400:5"/>as not to defend themselves against such injust violence, and in the strength of the Lord to adhere unto their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer principles, with much boldnes of spirit, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart, in this certainly we shall have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and the Lord shall be with us.</p>
            <p>We are not so, to have the one of our eyes upon the Sectaries, as not to hold the other upon the Malignants, they being an enemy more numerous, and no lesse sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and powerfull nor the other, and at this time more dangerous unto us, not only because experience hath proven that there is a greater aptitude and inclination in these of our land, to complie with Malignants then Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, that they carry on their wicked designes under a pretext of being for the King, but also because there be many of them in our own bowels; and for that they doe pretend to be for maintenance of the Kings Person and Authority, (and which is the matter of our griefe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the King ownes their principles and wayes, which if it be not taken heed unto, may prove a great snare, and dangerous tentation to many to side with them against the Lords people, and his cause. The constant tenour of the carriage of these in this land, who stand for the cause of God, are undeniable arguments of their affection to Monarchy, and to that Royall Family and Line which hath sweyed the Scepter of this Kingdom for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeers past; albeit his Majestie who lately reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, refused to harken to their just desires; yet did they with much patience and moderation of mind, supplicate and solicite his Majesty for satisfaction in these things that concerns Religion and the Covenant, and were still willing, that upon satisfaction given, he should be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the exercise of his Royal power, &amp; whatsoever envie and malice objects to the contrary, were careful to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101400:6"/>get assurance concerning the safety of his Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, when they brought their Army out of <hi>England,</hi> and when notwithstanding of that assurance, the prevailing party of Sectaries were acting his life, did to the utmost of their power, endeavour by their Commissioners that there might have been no such proceeding, and when their de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires and endeavours were not succesefull, did protest and bear testimony against the same. And as both Kirk and State had testified their tender respect to his Majesty who now reigns, by their Letters written to him whilst his Father was yet living, so no sooner did the Parliament heare of his Fathers death, but they did with all solemnity proclaim him King of these King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and after they had acquainted his Majesty by Messages with their proceedings herein, Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were sent both from State and Kirk instructed with power and Commission to expresse the Affection of this Kingdome to Monarchy, and his Majesties Person and Government, together with their desires concerning the security of Religion, and the Peace of those Kingdoms. And albeit the desires of both which are now published to the world, with his Majesties answers thereto, are such as are most just and necessary; yet the Counsels of the malignant party had so great influence upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, that his answers are not only not satisfactory, but short of that which was many times granted by his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Father, and cannot be acquiesced unto, unlesse we would abandon the League and Covenant, and betray Religion, and the cause of God.</p>
            <p>We hold it the duty of all who live in this Land, to wrestle with God in the behalfe of the King, that he may be recovered out of the snare of evill Counsell, and brought to give satisfaction to the publick desires of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101400:6"/>Kirk and State, and in their places and stations, to use all endeavours with himselfe and others for that effect, and to be willing, upon satisfaction given, to admit him to the exercise of his power, and cheerfully to obey him in all things according to the will of God, and the Lawes of the Kingdom, and to do every thing that tends to the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Majesties Person, and just greatnesse and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in the defence and preservation of the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties of the Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>But if his Majesty, or any having, or pretending power and Commission from him, shal invade this Kingdom, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretext of establishing him in the exercise of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power, as it will be an high provocation against God to be accessory or assisting thereto, so wil it be a necessary duty to resist &amp; oppose the same. We know that many are so forgetful of the oath of God, &amp; ignorant &amp; careles of the interest of Jesus Christ &amp; the Gospel, and doth so little tender that which concerns his Kingdom &amp; the Privileges thereof, &amp; doth so much dote upon absolute &amp; Arbitrary Government for gaining their own ends, &amp; so much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne the Instruments of the work of Reformation, that they would admit his Majesty to the exercise of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power upon any termes whatsoever, though with never so much prejudice to Religion, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of these Kingdomes, would think it quarrell enough to make Warre upon all those who for conscience sake cannot condescend thereto; but We desire all these who feare the Lord, and mind to keep their Covenant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to consider these things which followes, first. That as Magistrates and their power is ordained of God, so are they in the exercise thereof, not to walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their owne will, but according to the Law of equity and righteousnesse, as being the Ministers of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101400:7"/>of GOD for the safety of His People; Therefore a boundles and illimitted power is to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in no King nor Magistrate, neither is Our King to be admitted to the exercise of his Power as long as he refuses to walk in the Administration of the same, according to this rule, and the established Laws of the Kingdom, that his Subjects may live under him a quiet and peaceable life in all Godlinesse and honestie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is ane mutuall Obligation and Stipulation betwixt the King and his People, as both of them are tied to GOD, so each of them are tied one to another for the performance of mutuall and reciprocall duties, according to this: It is Sature and Ordained in the 8. Act of the 1. Parliament of King <hi>James</hi> the 6. That all Kings, Princes or Magistrates whatsomever, holding their place which hereafter shall happen in any time to Reign and bear rule over this Realm, at the time of their Coronation and receit of their Princely Authority, make their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promise by Oath in the presence of the Eternal GOD, that during the whole course of their lives, they shall serve the same Eternall GOD to the utmost of their power, according as he hath required in His most Holy Word contained in the Old and New Testament, and according to the same Word, shall maintain the true Religion of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> the Preaching of His most Holy Word, and due and right Administration of His Sacraments now received and preached within this Realm, and shall abolish and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainstand all false reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion contrary to the same, and shall rule the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge according to the Will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of GOD revealed in His Word, and according to the lovable Laws and Constitutions received within this Realm, and shall procure to the utmost of their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101400:7"/>power to the Kirk of God and whole Christian People, true and perfect peace in all time coming, and that Justice and Equity be keeped to all creatures without exception, which Oath was sworn, first by King <hi>James</hi> the 6. and afterwards by King <hi>Charles</hi> at his Coronation, and is inserted in our Nationall Covenant, which was approven by the King, who lately Reigned: As long therefore as his Majesty who now Reignes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuses▪ to hearken to the just and necessary desires of State and Kirk, propounded to his Majesty for the Security of Religion, and safety of his People, and to engage and oblige himself for the performance of his Duty to his People: It is consonant to Scripture and reason, and the Laws of the Kingdom, that they should refuse to admit him to the exercise of his Government, untill he give satisfaction in these things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the League and Covenant which hath been so solemly sworn and renewed by this Kingdom, the Dutie of defending and preserving the Kings Majesties Person and Authority, is joyned with ane subordinate unto the dutie of preserving and defending the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberties of the Kingdoms: And therefore his Majestie standing in opposition to the just and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary publick desires concerning Religion and Liberties, it were a manifest Breach of Covenant, and a preferring of the Kings interest to the Interest of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> to bring him to the exercise of his Royall power, which he walking in a contrary way, and being compassed about with Malignant counsels, cannot but imploy unto the prejudice and ruin of both.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Was not an Arbitrary Government and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited power, the fountain of most of all the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both in Kirk and State? And was it not for restraint
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101400:8"/>of this and for their own just defence, against Tiranny and injust Violence, which ordinarily is the fruit and effect of such a power, that the Lords People did joyn in Covenant, and have been at the expense of so much blood, pains and treasure these yeers past, and if his Majestie should be admitted to the exercise of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment before satisfaction given, were it not to put in his hand that Arbitarity Power, which we have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on just and necessary grounds been so long withstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and so to abandon our former Principles, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary our Cause.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The King being averse from the Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and the instruments thereof, and compassed about with Malignant &amp; disaffected men, whom he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens unto as his most faithfull Counsellers, and looks upon as his best and most Loyall Subjects: We leave it to all indifferent men to judge, whether his Majestie, being admitted to the exercise of his Power before sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction given, would not by such Counsells endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour an overturning of the things which GOD hath wrought amongst us, and labour to draw publick administrations concerning Religion and the liberties of the Subject, unto that course and channell in which they did run under Prelacie, and before the Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation? Which we have the more cause to fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Royall Father did so often declare, that he conceived himself bound to imploy all the power that GOD should put in his hands to the utmost for these ends; and that he adheres as yet to his Fathers Principles, and walkes in his way, and hath made a Peace with the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebells, by which is granted unto them the full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Popery.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is no strange nor new thing for Kingdoms to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101400:8"/>preserve Religion and themselves from ruine, by putting restraint upon the exercise of the power and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those who have refused to grant those things that were necessary for the good of Religion, and the Peoples safety; there hath been many precedents of it in this and other nations of old, and of late upon these and other important considerations: It shall be the wisdom of every one who dwells in the Land, to take heed of such a temptation and snare, that they be not accessory to any such designes or endeavours, as they would not bring upon themselves, and upon their families, the guilt of all the detriment that will undoubtedly follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to Religion and the Covenant, and of all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series and calamities that it will bring upon his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Person and throne, and upon these Kingdoms; such a thing would in all appearance be the undermining and shaking, if not the overthrowing and destroying of the work of Reformation; and therefore whosoever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the same, oppose themselves to the Cause of GOD, and will at last dash against the Rock of the LORDS Power, which hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces many high and lofty ones since the beginning of this Work in these Kingdoms, and it is unto us a sure Word of Promise, That whosoever shall associate themselves, or take counsell together, or gird themselves against GOD and His Work, shall be broken in pieces.</p>
            <p>It is not onely joyning in Arms with the Malignant partie, that all these who would keep their integritie has need to beware of, but also subtill devices and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes that are promoted by fair pretexts and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to draw men to dispence at least with some part of these necessarie desires that are propounded to his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101400:9"/>Majestie for securing of Religion, after many turnings and devises the foundation of the Unlawfull Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was at last laid by his Majesties Concessions of the date the year 1648. wherein though many things seemed to be granted, yet that was denied, without which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the Union betwixt the Kingdoms could not have been secured, and it is probable, that such a way may be assayed again, and prosecuted with very much cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and skill to deceive and insnare the simple: It doth therefore concern all ranks and conditions of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to be the more warie and circumspect, especially in that which concerns the Nationall Covenant, and the Solemn League and Covenant, that before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie be admitted to the exercise of his Royall Power, that by and attour the Oath of Coronation, he shall assure and declare by his Solemn Oath under his hand and seal, his allowance of the Nationall Covenant, and of the Solemn League and Covenant, and obligation to prosecute the ends thereof in his Station and Calling, and that he shall for himself and his successours, consent and agree to Acts of Parliament, injoyning the Solemn League and Covenant, and fully Establishing Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Government, the Directory of Worship, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Faith and Catechisme, as they are approven by the Generall Assembly of this Kirk and Parliament of this Kingdom, in all his Majesties Dominions, and that he shall observe these in his own Practise and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, and that he shall never make opposition to any of these, nor endeavour any change thereof; Albeit the League and Covenant be dispised by that prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party in <hi>England,</hi> and the Work of Uniformity, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the retardments and obstructions that hath come in the way, be almost forgotten by these Kingdoms, yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101400:9"/>the obligation of that Covenant is perpetuall, and all the duties contained therein are constantly to be minded, and prosecuted by every one of us, and our posterity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their place and stations; and therefore we are no lesse zealously to endeavour, that his Majestie may Establish, and swear, and subscribe the same, then if it were unamimously regarded and stook unto by all the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> his Majestie swearing and subscribing the League and Covenant, will much contribute for the Security of Religion, his Majesties happinesse, and the Peace of his Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>As it is incumbent to all, who live in this Kirk and Kingdom, to be watchfull and circumspect, so it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns these of the High and Honourable Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their Committees, in a speciall way to see to their dutie, and to be straight and resolute in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the same; Their former proceedings is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us a sufficient evidence and ground of hope, that they will not be wanting in any necessary testimony of dutie and Loyalty that they owe to the King, by using all just and seasonable endeavours for obtaining satisfaction of his Majestie, that so he may be established upon his Thrones; And we trust, that upon the other hand, the sence of their obligation to GOD, and his Oath that is upon them, will make them constantly to adhere to their former Principles, and resolutions, and desires concerning Religion and the Covenant, that reall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction may be had thereanent, before the King be put in the exercise of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s power, and that they will care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provide for the safety of the Kingdom, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of intestine dangers, and in regard of invasion from without: It is not long since they, together with the rest of the Land, made solemn Publick Confession
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101400:10"/>of Compliance with Malignants, carnall confidence, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of self interests, and hearkening to the Counsells of flesh and blood, and did in a speciall way engage themselves to comply, and seek themselves and their own things, no more to abandon the counsels of their own hearts, and not to rely upon the Arm of flesh, and to purge Judicatories, and Armics from Profane, and scandalous persons; And God forbid that they should so soon forget, or neglect so necessary duties, and fall again unto so great and grievous transgressions. We trust that they will seek the things of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and not their own things, that they will hearken to His Word, and not walk in the imaginations of their own hearts, that they will relie upon the Arm of the LORD, and not upon the arm of flesh, that they will be warie and circumspect in decerning the dispositions and affections of those whom they put in trust; and that seeing this Kingdom hath so much smarted, and been so often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by compliance with Malignants, that they will carefully avoid this snare of those who were upon the former Unlawfull Engagement, and be tender in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of such; And we cannot but exhort them in the Name of the LORD, to take notice of the Oppression of the People and Commons in the Land, by the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse exactions of Land-Lords, Collectours and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. We do not justifie the murmurings and grudgings of those, who preferring the things of the world to the Gospel and things of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> repine at neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary burthens, without which it is not possible that the Land can be secured from invasion without, and insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection within, or the Cause and People of GOD de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from enemies: It is the duty of every one who hath taken the Covenant, willingly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a cheerfull
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101400:10"/>mind to bestow their means and their pains as they shall be called thereunto, in an orderly way; yet should these to whom God hath committed the Government, take care that they be not needlessely burthened, and that none grind their faces by oppression; not only by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Lawes against the same, but by searching out of the cause of the poor, and by executing these Lawes ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously upon these that oppresse them, that they may find real redresse of their just grievances and complaints, and be encouraged to bear those burthens which cannot be avoyded.</p>
            <p>As the Parliament have begun, so we hope they will continue, to purge out all these from trust, that are not of known integrity and affection to the cause of God, and of a blamelesse and Christian conversation, and that they and the Officers of the Army in their respective pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, will seriously mind, and speedily and resolutely goe about the removing from the Army all malignant and scandalous persons, and also the removing of Sectaries when any shall be found therein, that they may give real evidence that they did not deal deceitfully with God, in the day that they engaged themselves thereto.</p>
            <p>Albeit wee hope and pray that those who beare charge in our Army, will from the remembrance of the Lords goodnesse to them, and the honour that he hath put upon them, endeavour to carry themselves faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and straightly, yet it cannot be unseasonable to warn them to take heed of tentations, and to beware of snares that they be not drawn to indifferencie or neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the cause of God, much lesse unto connivance at, or compliance with the courses and designes of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or Sectaries, but to stick closely by the same, and to be zealous against all the enemies and adversaries
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101400:11"/>thereof, and it concerns souldiers to be content with their wages, and to doe violence to no man, but as they are called unto the defence of the cause and people of God so to behave themselves in such a blamelesse and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian a way, that their carriage may be a testimony to his cause, and a comfort to his people, so shall our Armies prosper, and the Lord shall goe out with them.</p>
            <p>But most of all it concerns the Ministers of the Gospel whom God hath called to give warning to his people to look to their duty; It is undeniably true, that many of the evils wherewith this Kirk and Kingdome hath been affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in our age, have come to passe, because of the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of some, and corruptions of others of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, whilst some fell asleep, and were carelesse, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were covetous and ambitious, the evil man brought in Prelacy, and the Ceremonies, and had farre promoted the Service-Book, and the Book of Cannon, and the course of backsliding and revolting was carried on, untill it pleased God to stirre up the spirits of these few, who had stood in the gap to oppose and resist the same, and to begin the work of Reformation in the Land; since which time, the silence of some Ministers, and compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of others, hath had great influence upon the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sliding of many amongst the people, who upon the discovery of the evill of their way, complain that they got not warning, or that if they were warned by some, others held their peace, or did justifie them in the course of their backsliding; We can look upon such Ministers no otherwise then upon those that are guilty of the blood of the Lords people, and with whom the Lord will reckon for all the breach of Covenant, and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that hath been in the Land. The Priests <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> preserve knowledge, and they should seek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101400:11"/>mouth, for he is the messenger of the Lord of Hosts; but such are departed out of the way, and have caused many to stumble at the Law, therefore hath the Lord made them contemptible and base before all the people, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they have not kept his wayes, but have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall in his Law, because they have lost their savour, he hath cast out many of them as unsavoury salt, but such as have been saithfull, as he hath preserved them from the violence and fury of men, so hath he verified his word in their mouthes, both against his enemies, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his people, and his work, and makes them see, though not all their desires concerning the Gospel, and the work of God in the land, yet very much of the fruit of their labour, by preserving the doctrine and all the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Jesus Christ in their purity, and adding in some measure thereto the power and life thereof: We doe therefore charge all the Ministers of the land, before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing in his Kingdom, as in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing to be ensamples of a good conversation, and to walk without offence, that the Ministry be not bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; So to take heed unto the flock over which the Holy Ghost hath made them overseers, to declare unto them all the Counsell of God, and to give them timous warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerning every danger and duty, and to hold forth unto them the solid grounds of reall consolation, by which they may be encouraged and comforted in all their trials and afflictions, that they may be free of the blood of all men, and have this as a ground of rejoycing, even the testimony of their consciences, that in simplicity and godly purenesse, not with fleshly wisdome, but by the grace of God they have had their conversation in the world, and have exhorted and comforted, and charged
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101400:12"/>every one committed unto them as a Father doth his children; especially, Ministers are to be carefull to be much in discovering the temptations, and pressing the duties of the times, that these who are under their charge may know what to avoyd, and what to embrace and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue. If all the Watchmen in the Land shall give warning, and blow the Trumpet at once, it shall not be easie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to prey upon the people of God; Wee know no cause why any whom God hath called to preach the Gospel, should be afraid to speak boldly in the Name of the Lord, since God hath given so manifest a testimony of his care and protection, in preserving them these yeers past, who have striven to be faithfull to him who hath called them from all the fury and malice of the haters of the work of God, and of the Kingdom of his Sonne Jesus Christ, who hath promised to be with his servants unto the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Albeit the Land be involved in many difficulties, and compassed about with great and imminent dangers, yet there is hope and ground of consolation concerning this thing, the Lord is in the midst of us, and we are called by his name, our eares hear the joyfull sound of the Gospel, and our eyes see our Teachers. We behold the Arme of the Lord stretched out daily in working salvation for his people, and answering their desires upon their enemies, by terrible things in righteousnesse, although we be but few in number, yet the Lord of Hosts is with us, and in the power of his strength, we shall be able to prevaile, although our land be filled with sin, yet we have not been forsaken of the Lord our God, but he hath alwayes had compassion upon us, and delivered us in all our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, although some of understanding fall, it is but to try, and to purge and to make white even to the end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101400:12"/>it is yet for a time appointed, although many cleave to us by flatteries, yet there be a remnant who keep their integrity, and the Lord shall doe good to these that be good, but such as turn aside to crooked wayes, shall be led forth with the workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>The Lords people in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the cause and Covenant, may be perplexed, but shall not despaire, they may be persecuted, but shall not be forsaken, they may be cast down, but shall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed; and although uniformity, and the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in these lands, seem not only to be retarded, but almost pluckt up by the roots, and the foundations thereof razsed; yet the seed which the Lord hath sowen there, shall again take root downward, and bear fruit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; The zeale of the Lord of Hosts shall performe this.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. KER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>